hello and welcome this is active
inference guest stream number
91.1 on November 1st
2024 we're with John daglio at all
discussing dual aspect monism and the
free energy principle we'll have a
presentation by John followed by a panel
discussion so thank you all for joining
and John for the presentation
to
you okay thanks Daniel and thanks very
much to active inference Institute uh
for for hosting this uh and and thank
you so much to um all of uh my
colleagues and uh people I very much
look up to and uh uh such brilliant
figures in the field for for joining uh
for this um so I'm going to be speaking
about um the free energy principle and
dual aspect monism
specifically from a leanian neuros
psychon analytic perspective um and I'll
say a little bit about what kind of
background I'm I'm bringing from from
the leanian Viewpoint um it's a
particular School of
psychoanalysis uh that has mostly
engaged less with contemporary Natural
Sciences and I think that this
engagement is very fruitful and
introduces some uh not necessarily new
ideas but uh different sort of angles
and perspectives and so I'm really much
hoping for for a discussion and um
around these ideas um but to be to begin
with a a joke uh that maybe illustrates
some of the ideas um this is actually
this is a joke for the hegelian subject
um but I think it would equally apply to
the leanian subject um as uh the the
lenan subject or hegelian subject not as
something that is um a simply
straightforward uh conscious being but a
certain uh uh self-contradiction or a
certain self-loop um uh of uh uh uh the
diverting out of One's Own Self um and
so so the joke goes um that uh the
subject emerges precisely by way of a
reflective self-relating reapplication
of a logical operator as in the worn out
joke about the cannibal who ate the last
cannibal in the tribe uh so and and uh
these sort of um twists um show up in a
lot of um the sort of philosophy behind
here but I I think that uh the idea is
linked quite well um to uh some of the
computational concepts that I'll be
talking about so with that um these are
some of the um sources I'm drawing on
this is a book recently published um uh
uh I'm very grateful for uh Mark and
Carl for um such kind endorsements and
um an article that recently came out in
the journal neuros pych analysis
discussing some of these ideas in a
little more specific philosophical depth
um but to begin um I I I begin with uh
uh SS's work on dual aspect monism and
just uh to give the background uh dual
aspect monism is a philosophical
position
um coming from Spinosa where it doesn't
uh posit some sort of dualism uh from
this cartisian tradition uh rather
there's just sort of one stuff in nature
um I'm calling it thing in nature um but
there's just kind of one thing Freud
called it the mental apparatus and the
and this is the monism part of it and
the Dual aspects come from the fact that
we have two Vantage points for this one
part of nature you can look at this part
of nature uh as a subject um with
thoughts feelings and the like and you
can look at this part of nature as an
object um the brain the thing that you
can poke uh squeeze measure all of those
things and the idea is that uh neither
is more real than the other uh these are
two perspectives of the same unique part
of nature it's not like the liver which
does all wonderful things of filtering
toxins out of the body um but presumably
there's not something it's like to be be
a liver um uh in the way that there's
something it is like to be the brain
that there is a a subjective experience
that the brain has and likewise there's
a subjective Vantage Point uh on this uh
thing in nature but let me just uh
make okay great so these are two uh
lenses uh neither is necessarily more
real than the other um but interestingly
this leaves this kind of question of
okay well then what is this thing in
nature um how can we describe this thing
in nature uh if it's neither uh uh
physiological nor subjective what is it
then um and recent work um has has
argued and tried to apply the free
energy principle um to characterizing
the the nature of this ontology uh to
characterize the nature of nature so to
speak and um the argument is that um
ultimately uh for any what's called a
self-organizing system any system which
is bound by a barrier that distinguishes
system from not system uh obeys what's
called friston's law and friston's law
as uh everyone here knows um uh is that
um all quantities within the system that
can change will change to minimize free
energy um minimizing free energy being
um a way of saying there's a
minimization of uh uncertainty uh
there's a minimization of entropy um
minimization of error signals
essentially and I realize there are some
mathematical differences but um this
this is the general picture um so the
argument is that this
thing here uh can be characterized as
obeying these sort of informatic
principles of minimizing uncertainty
minimizing surprise and all of the
operations here can likewise be uh
characterized as um changing in order to
deal with um free
energy so that being said um I I I want
to take this and and think through um uh
Mark SS's recent work on the hard
problem of consciousness
and specifically his Arguments for what
then are the necessary mechanistic
features for a conscious self-organizing
system so not just sort of things in
nature in general but specifically this
this part of nature that has this very
remarkable quality of being conscious um
and how do we characterize this how do
we understand it um from a free energy
principle perspective and so the first
main point is that um within this system
there are multiple categories of uh
homeostatic demand uh and and here um
the the main references are um innate
categories of um especially emotional uh
homeostasis but not only also bodily
homeostasis for example um uh viable
bounds for blood sugar concent uh levels
for sodium concentrations but also more
socio emotional things like it is good
for the system to for the organism to be
close to caregivers um it is good to
avoid threats to life and limb in the
prehistoric jungle when the prehistoric
tiger is running at the poor prehistoric
human the one who has um wants to avoid
said prehistoric tiger um is going to
survive um it's going to maintain the
Integrity of the system uh and so the
argument is that within this uh system
especially in mamalian brains there are
many there are many of these categories
um I'm not going to list all of them um
perhaps can talk about them later if it
becomes relevant but there are these
different systems that um are different
uh affective uh qualities uh I've
mentioned a few um say attachment
demands say um demands for engaging with
novelty uh say demands or saying uh
staying safe from threats to to to harm
and computationally speaking all of
these systems function as what's called
hyper priors or innate prior predictions
uh So within the model um these are
predictions that one the organism uh is
born with and two uh they can't change
uh so you can't change your set point
for temperature bounds because if you do
then you dissipate and proteins don't
like that um so and likewise for uh uh
these socioemotional homeostats of
saying uh it is good to stay close to
caregivers um these hyper prior do not
change and so the the the system has to
deal with them it has to sort of re with
the fact of these things um
and therefore in the very chaotic
context of um uh uh existing um not only
in the prehistoric jungle but also in
the complicated interpersonal social
life that humans especially find
themselves in there are many different
contexts and more specifically many
unpredicted contexts um there's no way
that Evolution could have predicted that
we'd be living in the current kind of
society we're living in that's not sort
of ENC into the into the genome um but
what this means is that there has to be
some mechanism within the brain for
prioritizing which um category uh am I
going to uh focus on or allow to sort of
guide my predictive Cascades in this
given context um uh uh in in this given
uh situation am I going to follow um
hunger predictive Cascades am I going to
uh um I might be hungry right now but
I'm I'm having some sort of thing I want
to say uh so I'm prioritizing something
else um when uh uh you are uh holding a
hot cup of coffee um but you have a goal
of wanting to not spill that because you
know that might be frustrating you then
you tolerate um the pain that you feel
uh from the hot cup of coffee in your
hand rather than following the pain
Cascade to release the hand and drop it
um you are sort of following a different
um line of prediction um for for a
moment um when the child is faced with
uh the conflict of okay my loving
caregiving um uh uh caregiver is not
doing what I want them to do right now
um that's making me a little angry I'm
actually feeling like I want to destroy
and attack um this caregiver but oh no
that doesn't uh line up well with um my
demands to stay close and um sort of
stay protected by this caregiver if I
destroy uh uh the caregiver then there's
no one for me to be close to so I have
to choose which one am I going to
prioritize um uh especially in
unpredicted
contexts uh within that prioritization
is the capacity for Choice um there's
the capacity to voluntary um action um
at this basis so these five uh uh
features are are are what Mark has
argued are the sort of core features of
um an affectively conscious
self-organizing system and it's within
this model that I want to think about
okay um what uh does the leanian
perspective kind of add to this and
specifically what how does this uh open
questions for thinking about the free
energy Principle as we apply it to uh
how we think about especially human
ontology um within this uh we can say
however that all of these mechanisms all
of these uh functions that are necessary
uh for their to be uh affective
Consciousness that sort of subjective
quality of uh feeling of what it's like
to be uh uh conscious which is a certain
kind of feeling State um all of those
obey First's law uh that is um uh they
the prioritization function operates in
order to minimize free energy and how
does it do it um this is the the
argument that affective Consciousness uh
corresponds to Precision modulation so
there are not only within the free
energy Principle as again we all know
predictions and prediction errors these
are all weighted by Precision weights
basically the the confidence in how how
confident am I that this prediction will
minimize free energy uh likewise how um
Salient are these prediction errors um
should I be attending to them or not can
I just dismiss them um and the Precision
weights um are uh uh uh modulated
depending on which which of the uh
homeostatic systems gets prioritized so
for example to go back to the poor child
who has to deal with um conflicts of
rage and attachment um uh prioritizing
rage adjusts different predictions that
are more likely to minimize um the the
prediction errors relating to rage the
frustrations around that um uh attack uh
destroy um uh cry complain um uh uh uh
teeth and things like that versus um uh
attachment uh prioritizing attachment
needs would lead to a different um uh
modulation different Precision weights
would um be increased others would be
decreased that are associated with more
affiliative or bonding um
Cascades and when it comes to situations
of uncertainty where the organism does
not know what to do uh the
prioritization here allows one and this
is uh the the argument for why why
affects are conscious or why this
Precision modulation is conscious is
that feeling one's way through one's
predictions it's not just that the
Precision weights change that's the sort
of what we see um thinking from
objectively but when we think about it
subjectively this this is just feeling
when you feel your way through your
predictions you're able to feel okay
this feels better good in a certain way
this feels bad worse in in a certain way
this allows me to sort of feel my way
through conditions of uncertainty when I
don't know what to do and I have to
create I have to explore I have to
invent um uh I use affect as a guide uh
and this is the the homeostatic function
of affect uh and it is in this way that
affect facilitates the minimization of
free energy in the long term for the
system um this idea of feeling one's way
through one's
predictions uh okay
so um thinking philosophically here then
what uh what this position argues is
that friston's law and the the uh
formulas of the free energy principle
explain the operations of the mental
apparatus that ontological level in both
of its appearances in both uh
subjectively it explains um the the the
qualia and subjective experience of
affect affective consciousness and
objectively it explains various neuronal
Dynamics neuroc Cascades um specifically
uh neuromodulatory control of post
synaptic gain um via these uh uh or
homeostatic uh command
systems and what this allows us to sort
of try to begin Furnishing I think this
is what's so exciting um regarding the
philosophy of the fre energy principle
is that we can begin to articulate uh
what I'm calling an informatic ontology
um one that is neither physiological nor
um subjective but this something else of
what it is it's it's has something to do
with information it has something to do
with minimizing uncertainty and how we
go about dealing with
uncertainty
okay what does Lan have to do with any
of this um and so um Lan uh was a French
psych analyst who is very famous for
arguments around language uh arguing
that um one of his perhaps his most
famous argument is that the unconscious
is structured like a language and uh
this leads to many arguments and Lon was
notoriously known and leanians today are
even more notoriously than Lan I think
known for being remarkably
anti-naturalist uh and but this is maybe
an illustrative quote uh so this is from
an interview I think I I think when Lan
was at MIT or I think somewhere in the
states um we think with our we think we
think with our brains personally I think
with my feet that's the only way I
really come into contact with anything
solid I do occasionally think with my
forehead but only when I bang into
something uh but I've seen enough eegs
to know that there's not the slightest
trace of a thought in the brain um this
is not the only comment Lon makes like
this but it it carries a certain
sentiment that um and S sort of
background for this audience which I
know may not necessarily be leanian um
uh but uh leanian PCH analysis is very
uh this perhaps characterizes most
leanians as sort of not really
interested in engaging with the brain
that it's simply not relevant what we
care about is language um and that's all
we care about and it's unfortunate
because this really obscures a lot of
points Lan made and it really
misunderstands I think how Lan thought
about language and I think how Lan
thought about language is actually
incredibly consilient with uh the free
energy principle and this idea of
information
so this is a quotation from Lan
commenting on Freud's project for
scientific psychology and um this is a
drawing of that Freud has there on of
the the
neurons uh and and commenting on Freud's
use of thinking about neurons and trying
to think through this attempt to furnish
a psychology for neurologists and so on
um uh Lan says it is this this idea of
neurons that gives value to atomistic
theories the latter do not cover any of
those things they claim to cover namely
um uh a certain number of atoms of the
neuronic apparatus supposedly
individualized elements of the nervous
system neurons again but on the other
hand the theories of and relations of
contiguity and continuity illustrate
admirably the signifying structure as
such in so far as it is involved in any
linguistic operation so what L is saying
here is that these individ neiz elements
uh the sort of reductionist one might
even say approach of atomistic theories
of the nervous system actually
illustrate what he is thinking about
through the lens of language and
Linguistics um I think this is this this
is quite um different from saying that
it's language per se um and this is a
quote from seminar 20 um I say that the
unconscious is structured like a
language and I say like so as not to say
he says all the time that the
unconscious is structured by a language
the unconscious is structured like the
assemblages in question in set theory
which are like letters um I'm not going
to go into um Lan's um quasi mathematics
here uh but the idea here is that um uh
what is it the emphasis is on the word
like it's not um what language is by
language English German whatever it
might be um it is what is the nature of
language and specifically Lang anguage
as differential system
ofous and continuous
relations um and Lan argued proposed at
least was open to the idea that this can
be applied to the brain um again when
he's commenting on the project in
orientation to the object uh the
regulation of the threat the uh
ideational Representatives relate to
each other in accordance with the laws
of memory organization a memory complex
a facilitation um or a concention and I
emphasize here whose neuronic apparatus
perhaps allows us to Glimpse those
operations in a material form and whose
functioning is governed by the law of
the Pleasure
Principle uh again and I think this is
quite clearly showing how uh it's not an
emphasis on okay no it's only about
language it's an emphasis on okay these
um what linguistic operations uh
contiguity continuity can be glimpsed
and can appear likewise in the operation
of the brain I.E the the neuronic
apparatus here uh and more specifically
governed by the law of the pleasure
pleasure principle which um today we can
understand as the law of free energy
minimization and one last quote from Lan
because I think it's so remarkable here
um this is again in seminar 20 uh and
he's commenting on the on the status of
information theory in Natural Sciences
at the time in in the early 70s uh and
he's talking here that we're at the
level of the gene molecular information
and the winding of nuclear proteins
around strands of DNA that are
themselves right around each other
double helix and all of that and all of
this being tied together and sent via
hormonal links in other words messages
that are sent recorded and so on let us
note that the success of this formula
Finds Its Source in a Linguistics that
is not imminent but explicitly uh uh
formul not only imminent but explicitly
formulated in any case this action
extends right to the very foundations of
scientific thought being articulated as
and I emphasize negative entropy um a
negentropic function again a resistance
of dissipation toward um uh entropy of
the of the system uh so even at the
level of DNA what Lan is saying is you
can see something linguistic here surely
there is not speech at the level of DNA
in the sense of literal language being
exchanged as in what I'm saying right
now however it's the logic of
communication Theory um that that that
is uh relevant here and so what we can
say then is that when uh when when the
the symbolic or the the the system of
language that is referred to uh in
leanian theory what this refers to is
some kind of linguistic organization a
relation of different elements um uh uh
uh that are uh continuous uh in a chain
uh ones that relate to each other ones
that um are anticipatory one anticipates
the next um that revolve around a
certain
antagonism contradiction or
inconsistency and this is where um the
particular leanian twist I think comes
in it's that and this is what Lan means
by the real that um within any symbolic
system whether that's actual spoken
language or um the systems of DNA
communication um or um the neuronal
atomistic elements um within the brain
that there's some uh inconsistency some
uh tension that prevents a perfect
settling of the system it prevents a a
full sort of uh uh uh resolution uh
where there where there would be no
let's say uncertainty where there would
be no uh antagonism or attention or
arousal um and
importantly this inconsistency is not
some rued or imperfection to be remedied
or healed or done away with by um uh
good enough adaptation by um
a correction or sort of thing it's it's
something that's at the core of one's
being and Lan terms this this neologism
extimate condensation of exterior
intimate external internal um uh and the
idea is that what is most foreign to us
what is most alien to our sense of
ourselves is simultaneously what is at
the core of our self um it is
simultaneously what is uh most uh uh
precious what is most essential um to
how we think our conscious
self-reflective experience our let's say
egoic experience or even our symbolic
sense of where where we stand um in in
in our
organization so how can we then
conceptualize um this idea this idea of
a constit of a constitutive
inconsistency within some sort of
communicative or informatic system um uh
within this model within this model that
um SS has put forward regarding
affective Consciousness free energy
minimization uh and and the
like first um this requires a crucial
philosophical shift uh uh and and and
this is implicit for some uh uh not for
others but it it it Bears help by
stating it explicitly um uh and what
this is what I'm calling following
Adrian Johnston sort of what's called
capital N nature and this idea of
capital N nature is an idea that the
laws whatever those laws might be in
nature are fully determinate in that
they fully determine the behavior of
material particles they fully determine
what happens by stuff um generally and
simply speaking and two they are
seamless uh in other words they're
non-conflicting um they sort of govern
in a um sort of idealized fashion all of
the operations of whatever there might
be and in a wonderful exchange between
friston and I forget which um uh Journal
it was a philosophical critique of the
pre energy principle saying that okay
you're just you're just saying
everything's marov blanket so then you
get to use the feny principle to explain
everything um and I think the response
was wonderful it was like yes it is all
marov blankets all the way down um uh uh
and and one way of potentially reading
that um and in this um pre-print um uh
uh that you can find um from from Carl
friston is that uh this uh sort of uh uh
the mathematics that follow from
delineating things self organ or
self-organizing systems as delineated by
the possession of a marov blanket means
that you can actually apply this from
the very tiny things of quantum
mechanics all the way up through to the
macro scale of classical mechanics and
the argument here and this would be um
an anti-reductionist um nightmare is
that um all of the behavior of these
systems from very small to very large
can be subsumed within um a seamless
chain
of free energy uh uh minimization of
obeying something like friston's law as
it gets applied um in in these different
States and I am not by any means an
expert on the mathematics here so I I
welcome any um Corrections on that point
but um I think the fear for some would
be that okay you're saying everything
can be reduced to free energy
minimization and then this leads some
people to then say okay well no there
exists something that defies um a
reduction in this way and we can maybe
talk about it in a somewhat mystical way
as um you know uh being or something
purely negative uh uh or transcendental
like that now the alternative that I
want to put forward is that this is not
the only way to think about nature and
this is the perspective from Adrian
Johnson what he calls transcendental
materialism and weak nature so to speak
and weak nature uh refers to the idea
that um and it's it's a materialist
philosophical position there are only
natural material phenomena there is no
special transcendental subjectivity that
only exists because we speak um there is
no sort of special uh uh uh quasi
dualist but you might you don't want to
say the word dualist sort of a thing
that defies capture by uh any sort of
natural uh science or any sort of
material Theory there are only these uh
phenomena however the laws that govern
nature are not seamless uh they are not
uh fully able to assert themselves and
especially they do not uh uh sit in a
perfect harmony with each other
what I'm what I'm calling weak laws in
in contrast to strong laws that fully
determine and and uh line up a perfect
mathematical equation weak laws conflict
with each other and because of that
conflict fail to fully assert themselves
and therefore and this is this is how
the sort of transcendental Dimension
comes in here the more than natural
quote unquote phenomena that are
traditionally described as something
transcendental like human subjectivity
they emerge not in a determin IC fashion
out of the lower levels but they emerge
out of the conflicts and antagonisms of
those lower levels the points where weak
laws come into Rift with each other
where they bump up those points are
points of of non-determinate emergence
because they're not emerging from points
where determination is working the way
it would it comes sort of uh uh the
logic of an accident uh the logic of
emergence from something that's not
working um an emergence from some sort
of uh
antagonism uh and a way to kind of put
this formulaically complexity breeds
negativity um this negativity of what's
sort of not positivistic determined um
as things get more complex there are
more opportunities and more risks of
things short circuiting and more room
for things to go wrong and by go wrong
this means something new happens and
this sort of emergence by surprise and
you can think about this I this is
wonderfully wonderful book by Daniel
Milo um that uh you sometimes we think
of evolution as you know this strong uh
force of you adaptation it's well the
The evolutionary bar to survive and
reproduce is a relatively low bar um you
can have lots of things inherited think
of the number of genetic diseases that
get passed down because yeah and they're
not ideal those are not adaptive those
are not um the best for for for
minimizing um uncertainty and preserving
the state of the system nevertheless you
just need to live long enough to survive
and reproduce according to evolutionary
law it's not a strong law in the sense
of producing perfectly adaptive brain uh
or a brain without um conflicts that as
long as they don't um uh severely
undermine this um reproductive and
survival capacity they they can slip by
um and on the psych analytic or forian
side this is the argument and this is
not only um uh uh my argument this is or
from uh folks who work in in neuros
Psych analysis this is arguments from
within purely fian psych analysis as
well when Freud uh tries to argue for a
beyond the Pleasure Principle the sense
of a death Drive um drive toward inertia
um a drive towards sort of repetition as
an innate feature in a way he sort of
props up the Pleasure Principle as then
working to do its thing and then okay no
when the Pleasure Principle doesn't
excuse me work it's because there's some
Death Drive interfering and this is the
contrast argument that no there is no
beyond the Pleasure Principle this I'm
taking from Jonathan Lear uh there is
just the Pleasure Principle but the
Pleasure Principle is itself prone to
false repetitions of Prior satisfactions
leading it astray and so on simply put
the Pleasure Principle does its thing
but it it doesn't do it perfectly um
it's not a strong law um the law of the
Pleasure Principle is quote unquote weak
law
so I argue that we can find this kind of
uh logic at this point within the model
that uh SS has put forward so within
here there is the presence of multiple
categories of homeostatic demand that
have to be contextually prioritized in
conditions especially of
uncertainty what this is saying is that
within the brain within the level of
innate hyper priors within the
predictive model there are conflict uh
there are uh there is antagonism uh I
gave just one example the conflict
between attachment and uh uh rage where
you want to remove frustrations to your
goals these conflicts can easily be
multiplied among even just uh uh various
emotional socio emotional systems let
alone when we get into the problem of
having to think about the fact that
other self-organizing systems themselves
have in a hyper and they kind of depend
on them to help me with my stuff so I
need to take that into account there's
all of opportunities for
conflict um and not only that uh within
this model these uh different systems
cannot be uh uh uh equated into one
common denominator there is no sort of
um uh uh equation to say okay S10 of
seeking equals 34s of Rage equals 510 of
fear so you can add that up to get um I
don't know what the math would be but
whatever uh 20th percent of total
overall free energy um that equation can
happen because these are innate
categorically distinct um uh hyper
priors um uh what you need to do to deal
with attachment needs differs from what
you need to do to deal with Hunger
differs from what you need to do to deal
with um needs to explore and engage with
novelty and uncertainty so whichever and
you have to prioritize one because if
not then you're just sort of helpless
before this chaos um but in prioritizing
one you're necess neily um leaving
something else uh uh uncertain leaving
some residual surprise or or free energy
elsewhere um because these cannot be
fully uh subsumed under under one
category and so it is because of this
innate conflict this innate antagonism
that there is affective Consciousness um
affective Consciousness as the need to
feel your way through uncertainty to
feel your way through the predictions
you're employing in okay I don't know
which to prioritize here I'm going to
prioritize this but I'm not quite sure
what to do and then I have to kind of
feel what feels a little better what
feels a little worse this depends on
contradiction this depends on this
innate conflict between categorically
distinct domains of free energy all
within a single complex self-organizing
system um now um on the computational
side even though yes uh it is the case
that the brain does compute an overall
measure of quote unquote total free
energy or domain General free energy um
uh this does not eliminate the
difference between these domain specific
categories of free energy uh just
because the number is calculated to
allow computations and allow action
perception Cycles to occur uh to not
sort of just leave everything at a halt
so to speak this this should not be read
as doing away with this uh difference at
the level of the inate informatic
ontology uh uh that calculation
uh facilitates adaptive functioning
facilitates moving through the world but
it doesn't undo the fact that no there
is this conflict it's not a conflict
that is remedied um uh it's one that is
a constant sort of tension uh uh that
persists and so just going back to this
sort of diagram here um what we see not
simply that there's just some uh simply
existing thing there uh it's not just
some uh uh system which uh does its
thing of uh minimizing free energy well
no there's actually already there some
sort of antagonism or conflict uh uh
that problematizes a straightforward
application of friston's law uh it it it
it problematizes um in the sense that
well we're in situations all the time
where it's not clear what to do let
alone which systems prioritize uh to
perfectly minimize free energy and
pontic clinical phenomena testify to
this I think in a very clear fashion so
so um I just want to close on um uh the
main sort of questions I have um and
sort of ideas I have that I'm hoping we
can discuss in addition to to anything
else that comes up but I really want to
I'm curious and I really think you know
what are really like the consequences
for a self-organizing system which
contains categorically distinct and
contradictory domains of free energy uh
what does it mean to to think about the
free energy principle where there is
this sort of necessary Rift uh within a
conscious system of uh different uh
hyper priors uh that don't seamlessly
fit together uh they they don't form a
harmonious ho um and and this this
leaves a certain uh uh necessity for
conflict um what does it mean for the
for a system to uh obey friston's law
when the elimination of free energy is
um impossible if uh these innate
categories of free conflict with each
other uh in in this fashion and then
that's that's the the key point it's not
that um uh minimizing energy is just
because the environment is complicated
although it is and this introduces all
sorts of complications but it's also um
this this innate architecture of affect
of Consciousness where you have these
different domains of free energy um
where sort of almost by definition um
moving down One path uh means that
there's some residual or Surplus for
energy somewhere else hence we continue
to be conscious uh hence we uh uh never
eliminate uh our background uh uh
background level a minimal level of
uncertainty that's palpating through the
hierarchy um in other words uh what does
it mean uh uh when the system's efforts
to minimize free energy inevitably
produce uh free energy and this would be
again the the sort of leanian twist that
I'm coming from without stating all of
the leanian theory here that um uh
language itself produces its own
excesses it produces its own
uncertainties um so I'll leave it at
that and uh thank you very
much awesome thank you
John shall I stop sharing uh
sure okay whoever is moved
to let us begin with some initial
comments from the panel
um thank you John very much I'll I'll uh
dare to
start uh with some very small remarks uh
the the first and probably the main
remark is that I fear that um we are not
going to find anything to disagree about
um so how are we going to have an
interesting discussion if we all see
things the same way um so uh hopefully I
will be able to find something to
disagree with you about and so um in
that spirit let me let me
make one or two further remarks um you
invoke um my uh argument that the
different needs of a complex
organism um are have to be treated
categorically Ally uh they have to be
treated as categorical variables uh not
as as it happens because they require
you to do different things and those
different things conflict with each
other uh but uh because they each of
them have to be met in their own right
that's the crucial Point uh that it it
doesn't help to reduce the total
quantity of free energy if it if you
leave out one of the categories in other
words you always have to breathe as well
as drink as well as sleep Etc um so it's
in this sense that they they they they
they it's it's it's obligatory that they
be treated as categorical variables in
other words eight out of 10 of
sleepiness and eight out of 10 of thirst
are not the same thing they are
qualitatively different and incidentally
that for me is the ground zero of qualia
it's why we have to have different
qualities in the mind
um so you invoke that argument of mine
and I'm very uh glad to be to be cited
uh in in that way but I just want to
make the point that you don't need to
invoke that argument of mine which is as
it were built upon or even imposed upon
Call's um a bigger deeper uh uh free
energy principle I think that it's
inherent in Carl's own idea ideas uh for
example just to mention one and really I
could I could think of a few but the the
inherent antagonism between uh uh
complexity and
accuracy uh you could have you could
have cited that example which is really
a pretty basic principle a pretty basic
part of the um standard formalism that's
used uh by people working within Call's
frame work simply put um in in order to
maximize accuracy which is a good thing
uh you have to increase complexity which
is a Bad Thing uh in order to maximize
uh Simplicity which is a good thing you
have to Forfeit accuracy which is a Bad
Thing uh and so there's an inherent
antagonism there um and uh as I say I
can I could think of several others but
that's enough uh to to um make the point
uh in other words I want to make the
point that it's uh it's it's although
I'm glad to be cited in this context I
think that your argument applies to uh
to the the far more fundamental
formulation uh that that Carl uh has
given us then um one last point and
remember I'm just trying to get the ball
rolling and I'm trying to find is there
something we can disagree about um I I
I'm no philosopher by the way I'm such a
a badly educated philosopher that I
didn't even understand your joke at the
beginning about the cannibals uh but um
the um I'm no philosopher but the the
the the one thing that Jarred for me uh
if I understood you correctly is that
you're recommending that a dual aspect
monist uh metaphysics be replaced by a
transcendental materialist metaphysics
uh I can only assume that's what you're
saying because I don't see how you can
reconcile uh a materialist metaphysics
uh with a dual aspect monist metaphysics
and I because you know the materialist
is one side of the Dual aspects uh so
that's the one thing that Jarred for me
um I think that you know I I cling to
dual aspect monism because uh we want to
find a place in um Natural Science for
subjectivity the fact that it exists uh
here we are experiencing it right now
it's part of Nature and we have to find
some way uh of of of reconciling it with
our with our materialist conception of
the universe and uh for me the answer is
to uh to recognize that the material uh
perspect perspective is also a
perspective in other words there too
we're dealing with phenomena as observed
by sentient Minds The subjective and the
objective are both P perceptual uh
Vantage points upon something which lies
Beyond both appearances and that thing
which lies Beyond both appearances must
lie beyond the the the the phenomenal
properties of matter and that's why
Carl's hold way of thinking appeals to
me so profoundly you know the the idea I
mean it It ultimately goes back
Carl's way of thinking to Galileo
telling us that the book of nature is
written in the language of
mathematics um as I'm speaking I realize
um that there's one other thing I might
be able to disagree with you about but
let me stop there because I I I I I fear
I'm not going to be able to find
something
stronger to disagree with you about than
that thank
you sh shall I say something
or um so thank you uh thank you Mark um
and um I perhaps um uh after hearing
from some some other folks I'll I'll say
more uh less the point of disagreement
but more an open question that I have um
but at least regarding uh dual aspect
monism and transcendental materialism um
my my my sense is wanting to supplement
it not replace and I think this is where
there would be a a need to re theorize
something in transcendental materialism
as it has been theorized where um I
don't want to say transcendental
informatic ISM or I'm not a philosopher
um so I'm I'm not I'm not sure how to
say it but basically the to apply this
this way of thinking of uh uh uh weak
laws uh emergence from conflict
emergence from uh things not working uh
out uh uh that sort of thing to uh to
how we think about that whatever that
thing is in nature Beyond um both
phenomena so but the the way that I
interpret the materialism
in um transcendental materialism is
perhaps closer to um the the the idea of
information and this this is why um like
when Lan says the the Lan will say the
materiality of language um and this is a
materiality not necessarily in like the
the stuff that they can hold in
everything it's it's a it's an open
question I think but Lan uh and he
changes how he thinks about that through
over time but um in this sense of of the
idea of communication the idea of uh uh
information and negative
entropy oh maybe I can uh Al ask some
questions um thank you John first of all
uh it's such a pleasure to hear you kind
of tie together all of these different
threads um it's uh it's really
impressive um yeah the first point I'd
like to make is maybe um
um in relation to Adrien Johnston's uh
um transcendental materialism like there
is in his work also kind of some doubt
about how to formulate kind of his own
project I guess um he has this essay
from
2020 uh called um metat
transcendentalism and error first
ontology um where he says that he's come
to consider the descriptive label of
critical dialectical naturalism
synonymous to if not prefer able to
transcendental
materialism and then he says
specifically because for him it
condenses in a single phrase kind of
idealist methodology and then realist
materialist naturalist onology um so I'd
be yeah I'd be curious if there if if if
you have reasons to stick or prefer
transcendental materialism or uh whe
whether you would would consider these
um um in inter
interchangeable
um and and my other question um um maybe
also has an attempt to I guess stir the
pot in a way in terms of finding a point
of disagreement between between you and
Mark um not not for the sake of it but
because that's a question I'm quite
interested in um um you didn't mention
it today but uh since it's in the title
of enjoying uncertainty uh I'm curious
about this point of leanian Drive being
on the side of increases in
tension um and in that sense operating
outside or beyond the the logic of
homeostasis um as as I understand it in
your work um and I guess yeah I would I
would like to maybe push back a little
bit on that point um to the degree that
I wonder whether that kind of resistance
towards the concept of homeostasis
doesn't
have a lot if got most to do with kind
of lon's concept of
homeostasis uh because correct me if I'm
wrong but I think in seminar 2 he
defines it or he says something like you
know homeostasis can mean one of two
things the first is uh an equilibrium of
a system and the second thing is death
um and then 10 years later like in the
four fundamental concepts of of Psych
analysis kind of he repeats these same
points so I don't think it was it was a
quirk of that time um so I I do wonder
if like with the kind of more
contemporary concept of of homeostasis
including the seeking system and all of
the conflicts that you know arise in
that and that you uh um I think so
brilliantly kind of emphasize and and uh
uh put in the Forefront um yeah is it is
is that that rejection or that
resistance towards the concept of
homeostasis really necessary
yeah thanks ever and I and this would be
my uh yeah point for uh kind of question
potential disagreement um uh that if if
we then take the next step it's that at
this point uh that that I'm carving of a
of Consciousness as AR arising not from
uh free energy minimization but from the
contradiction and conflict of these
different not only categories ofers but
even um uh complexity accuracy
trade-offs um within the model that um
something else uh comes up there and and
uh one way that one way to think about
it is that okay yeah there's something
here um having to do with not just
trying to minimize uncertainty uh uh and
and at least and this is coming into
some more of the the the the clinical
Theory um but uh not not only about
minimizing uncertainty but finding a way
or the fact that um errors and
uncertainty is enjoyed in a certain way
and this is Lan's idea of j s um uh that
it's enjoyed not necessarily consciously
but uh enjoyed in uh in its own uh
unconscious or it's it's an enjoyment
that can't be experienced as such uh the
quote unquote strange satisfaction of
the symptom that that fre uh remarks
um but it's this I I I wonder and this
is what I was talking about with um okay
what does it mean for a system to try to
minimize free energy when
it's impossible to to reach that until
death um as is pointed out um
that yeah there's something about
um I think a proactive engagement and
enjoyment of uncertainty that I'm not
quite sure um is only seeking and this
is where I'm I I'm really curious uh
because seeking has its own certain
qualitative feel to it uh um the you
know enjoyment of uh uh no novelty
epistemic foraging uh you know the the
dog running around in the field and you
know having all fun and whatnot um uh
but that that that there there's also
these points where there's um uh
some kind of repetition or some kind of
either maintenance or increase of free
energy that has a certain uh enjoyment
to it um symptomatic enjoyment perhaps
and that at least from a leanian
perspective ultimately the goal is not
to minimize that free energy uh in the
sense of remove the tension uh the goal
is not to in to get rid of the symptom
or to replace the symptom with a better
thing or some better more um uh adaptive
plan uh it's to sort of confront this
logic of okay no there is something at
the core of one's being that exists
because things don't
work what's a way what's something that
can be done with that uh and this is
idea of of of enjoying one's symptom of
of uh uh uh and and this is where where
I I have questions like I don't know
what how to think about it necessarily
computationally but what would it be to
modulate uh something uh uh deep
predictions in that sense to modulate
them in such a way that uh they repeat
they continue to produce free energy
they continue to to lead to increases UN
in uncertainty but in a way that uh
allows the person to kind of uh find
find a a vivifying dimension uh uh to
that to to their symptom to find a
vivifying dimension
uh uh to how they go about uh managing
and uh enjoying uh uncertainty rather
than uh uh this at least the illusion it
makes to the system just trying to you
know totally get rid of it uh in a way
um and and I think that I think that's
where the lanan phys differs I think
from from how you've conceptualized it
Mark where there's it's not the idea
with um illegitimate predictions
maturely automatized predictions not
only the idea of laying down better ones
that can hopefully work and be more
adaptive but also to to do something
different with the prematurely
automatized predictions that um sustain
ones that are sort of your unique way of
dealing with the conflicts of these
different categories of free energy um
uh and and in that way to do something
different with it uh but yeah I'm I'm
not sure how that shows up or or how
that would uh play out
uh
[Music]
computationally I'm I'm going to resist
saying anything more until we've heard
from
call yeah I'm I'm the eldest so I have
to go last really but uh I can't resist
slipping in here um yeah that was a
wonderful presentation but actually your
last response was was revealing so I
learned quite a lot uh in terms of this
um the you know what Lan brings to the
table that you know may have to well I
imagine the ambition here is to sort of
naturalize that in terms of current
thinking about um about the way we
understand um senting Behavior and the
like um so um before I comment upon the
the two sets of questions which I
thought were fascinating what I've done
and this is really for Daniel I've gone
through whilst listening to the talk
identifying papers that um you may not
have referenced from other literatures
that I think lend weight to your a
number of specific points you made
during uh the presentation so if there's
time at some point close to the end um
I've got about four or five um actually
six papers that you might enjoy reading
completely outside I think your your
sort of sphere of reading
um that do pick up on some of the sort
of fundaments that you you were positing
as um key key parts of the argument so
I'm saying that uh just to forewarn you
that if I can at some point share my
screen and just flick through because I
know this has been recorded then you can
go back and have a look um to see if
anything is interesting ranging from
girdle's theorem to strange Loops you
know there's a lot of resonance with um
um other formulations outside the other
sphere in which we're talking um but
just come back to those sort of key
issues um perhaps in reverse order um so
this notion of um
enjoying the
uncertainty um or enjoying um um
paradoxical increases in free energy
um is there a mathematical formalism
that would um resolve that Paradox um or
sort of paradoxical um account um that
would also accommodate um Notions of
homeostasis as read by Lan um at the
same time could be read in terms of
self-organization from a physics
perspective or you so me from a panal
systems perspective um I two things
occur to me first of all your repeated
account of um
the um going Beyond just seeking um as
one ex manifestation of of this enjoying
your your
uncertainty um I I thought was very
interesting because I had assumed when
you started answering that this would be
exactly the epistemically expected
information game that underwrites
behavior so when people talk about
minimizing free energy that's fine um
when one's talking about sense making
but when one is talking about how we
engage with the world and the decisions
and the choices that we make or the
things that we select to do um then one
has to think about the expected free
energy expected following that choice or
decision or act or um uh intention um
and um from that perspective you know
the complexity and the accuracy that
Mark was referring to now become um risk
and ambiguity or when we Ed expected
Information Gain versus um expected cost
um and um the expected information G I
think does appear to have a lot of EX
simple expound um um capacity in talking
about the Allure of uncertainty and you
said that beautifully you talked about
novelty seeking you talked about um
epistemic foraging um and you know I was
surprised to hear that that for you
wasn't a sufficient explanation and
perhaps it's because you you were
associating um the epistemic foraging
with seeking of a particular uh of a
particular sort but a lot of what you
said um um seems to me to be exactly the
notion that we enjoy um um pushing the
boundaries in the fond hope or knowledge
that we will be able to resolve that
uncertainty and become wiser and more um
um more confident in our engagement you
with the world and it it reminds me very
much of an argument um put forward for
why we actively listen to music um
particularly jazz music uh which you
know has that exactly the right kind of
predictable unpredictability to keep us
engaged and I'm you know unusually the
argument here is that um I don't know
what's going to happen but I do know I
will know if I keep on doing this very
much like listening to a joke I don't
know what the punch line is going to be
but I do know if I commit to this this
uh your direction of travel then I will
be amused and some you know and that
Amusement that pleasure will be um if
you like scored by the resolution of
uncertainty in a volatile and unknown
space environment you
know in the space of jokes in that
instance um so I I you know I would and
I won't say anything more about that but
it'd be interesting if you could discuss
what is the this sort of um um essence
of enjoying uncertainty that is um not
explained by knowing I'm going to reduce
my uncertainty but first I have to
actually put myself in a situation where
I'm seeking out those uh you know that
potential for resolution of uncertainty
about me about mom about the jazz music
mathematically um I'm wondering whether
one way of sort of bringing Lan into the
21st century would be to go back to
something I found quite fascinating
which was the two ways of reading
homeostasis um as I understand it from
what ever was saying um so um death is
certainly one kind of homeostasis um but
clearly it's not the kind of homeostasis
that we associate with um biotic
self-organization and the mathematical
distinction between the two is between
equilibrium steady States and non-e
equilibrium steady States now all of
physics um and certainly kind of school
boy physics you you would have been um
exposed to uh when talking about
thermodynamic freey minimization
pertains to a point equilibrium so in
the language of um dyal systems the
we're talking about a point attractor so
at the point you converge to your point
ATT tractor everything ceases you're
dead you're cold you're a free energy
minimum um and you and that's a
perfectly apt description of closed
systems you know that is what will
happen if you isolated from a world but
when you're open to the world across um
your Markoff blanket for example um then
we're talking about a different kind of
equil a non-equilibrium uh steady state
and this has a characteristic itinerancy
I mean mathematically can um it's um and
I I can't resist slipping this in
because it it also uh appeals again to
sort of hel Hing ideas but in this
instance um it has to be the case in any
system that is far from equilibrium or
open to an environment that has attained
some kind of steady state I persists and
exists it has to have a solenoidal
aspect to it by the helm host
decomposition that is a mathematical
truism now there are many ways of
reading that solenoidal aspect it could
be a bi Rhythm it could be an
oscillation it could be um replication
Dynamics at an evolutionary scale it
could be walking it could be talking
could be my heart y everything that
returns to some point in a weak sense so
it's not exactly but returns to the
neighborhood and I just um I I just pick
up on that because of for many reasons
but specifically because of your the
repetition aspect of of this kind of um
um aspect uh sorry
of that um um the phenomenology that you
were talking about where where there is
exactly this description of the
particular itinerancy that
characterizes um free energy Minima that
are a result of attaining a
non-equilibrium steady state so you have
this iy there can't be any other way of
keeping within an attracting set unless
you keep returning to the point that
nearby point that you once that you were
once in so I'm just wondering if you
want to go beyond seeking and Beyond um
epistemic foraging um then perhaps what
you're saying is well yes but this is in
the context that I am on this attracting
set that has this quintessentially
biotic kind of um recurrence or or or or
repeatability that gives it an ey
tendency at at many many different time
scales that makes me the kind of thing
that I am
um and ex you know in this environment
in which you know to which to which I'm
I'm open so I just put that out there as
a possible mathematical metaphor for for
talking about sort of what Lan is
referring to if you want a physiological
metaphor I think it's important to
actually um distinguish now between
homeostasis homeor resis and allostasis
and aleris if there is such a thing so
the distinctions are the homeostasis is
fast reflexive whereas the anastasis
actually has some future pointing aspect
do it so you can plan to be homeostatic
but that in itself is not homeostasis it
you know it brings a certain uh depth
and itiner and one could argue in virtue
of the depth it takes you much closer to
the kind of structures and you know the
um Reliance upon um Precision modulation
that that you were talking to but
there's another um axis here which is
the difference between stasis and Reeses
so homeor resis is like homeostasis but
for paths and of course as soon as we're
talking about um systems that have
itinerant orbits where you do have to
keep revisiting characteristic states of
being at many many different time scales
then the kind of homeostasis what you're
talking about is now homeor resis is
actually keeping close to that path um
and I'm just wondering if Lan Lan's
distinction between the two kinds of
homeostasis was really a distinction
between mathematical homeostasis which
is a point of tractor and death and
homeor resis which is keeping to a path
uh or a set of paths that define an
orbit usually chaotic and it's usually
stastical far too much I'm come I'm
going to go back to the the the um
Mark's initial observation just to
celebrate that um so you um in my world
there's a distinction between between
categorical and continuous
variables um and I think Mark was
picking up on that and I think he was
absolutely right to do that I do think
that there's a really important role for
categorical generative models um in
relation to the description about sort
of symbols and language and sort of
carving nature into discrete ways of
being I think that's absolutely
essential and I'm sure you're right that
some unconscious um processing um You
probably takes place under discreet
language like um um generative models
and possibly also um conscious
processing um but the I think that's an
orthogonal argument from um the notion
the really important notion I think you
were you were trying to get across which
is that there are multiple
constraints um that um um provide
another kind of conflict because I've
got sort of multiple Dimensions that I
have to I have to um comply with it's
not just onedimensional pleasure there
is pleasure in multiple multiple
dimensions and sometimes some of the the
Excursion along one dimension may be
more um um unpleasurable than the
Excursion along another dimension and
that both of those if you like the
degree of Excursion will be very context
sensitive and hence I now have to
prioritize do I want to sort of be
homeotic in this Dimension or that Di
menion and I think Mark was trying to
say that it's the multi-dimensional
aspect that there are there are more
than one discrete Dimensions to um the
way that we have to um well
mathematically in terms of the extended
free energy evaluate the cost of this
particular plan um and that provides a
profound departure from things like
reinforcement learning where there's
only one um Dimension so I've now taken
to talking about not expected value or
utility but expected cost the negative
of that so I can now say that this
minimization of expected cost part of
the expected free energy um is
effectively a multiple constraint
satisfaction problem and it's usually if
you read the sort of you know the um the
math literature active inflence that's
usually incured by c um uh and one of
the reasons for C is it stands in for
constraints but it's multiple
constraints in every dimension that you
that there exists an outcome and of
course if you now condition C on some
inferred state of being or some context
um then you have exactly what you were
saying which is this problem of actually
prioritizing this constraint over over
over that
constraint the reason I like the word
constraint is that um you can now speak
to physicists who believe that the free
energy principle is dual to James's
constrained maximum entropy or caliber
principle the the entropy is for points
so that be the homeostasis the caliber
is for the path so that would be the
homeis so now you've got a way of
talking to physicists because what
you're saying is it's all in the
constraints and these constraints are
multiple there are as many dimensional
as as the dimensionality of of the phase
space so again I'm I'm just trying
trying to sort of um join um enable you
to sort of generalize you know these Rel
important points in a way that might
actually have a a relatively simple
mathematical um basis in fact it's
almost unavoidable um and certainly that
that notion of multiple constraints and
inducing a kind of conflict although you
are effectively in a multiple constraint
satisfaction resolving that con that
Conflict by prioritizing exactly as you
say those constraints what could also be
called prior preferences but um if you
think of a constraint or a cost as a
negative prior preference or preference
then then I think that all makes sense I
I got so much more to say but I'm going
to stop talking
now no thank you call that that's that's
really uh fascinating and this helps me
I think um maybe formulate what I'm
trying to think through from the from
the Lan end of things so I I think that
the the the the uh I think I think why
there would be um some suspicion of the
expected free energy calculation as this
sort of um uh the enjoying of engaging
with novel uncertainty and and that sort
of thing is because well um generally
when it sounds too adaptive um and you
know volans don't like that but um uh
the idea that the the the enjoyment um
doesn't derive from the fact that okay
I'm going to engage with this
uncertainty because and then I know that
I will get that pleasure in the end and
then it will meet that need that it's
it's um almost enjoyment for its own
sake um or the increase of uncertainty
almost for its own sake but what I think
would bring it together is that
um it would be uh and my use of the
terms might not be correct uh sort of
technically but the sort of uh ways of
thinking through the expected uh
uncertainty would be for uh an an
anticipated feature that never actually
material uh an anticipated um outcome
and this I think would maybe approximate
what what Lan calls the fantasy uh uh
and specifically the unconscious fantasy
which is not um it's not uh imagistic
it's sort of uh uh it's something that
is never uh uh formulated explicitly can
only be constructed um in the course of
a treatment but it's sort of um the
virtual terminal point upon which um
of of these scenes of increased
repetitions that don't work out um it
would be this sort of this increase of
uncertainty that leads to bad outcomes
um that doesn't ultimately lead to the
decrease of free energy um and yet it
repeats regardless uh and the the the to
rationalize that
um symptomatic let's say repetition is
by reference to some kind of fantasy
formulation of oh you know this is what
the this is the anticipated outcome that
the the person had that uh gives a
little sense to why this repetition was
happening why this repeated um uh
increase of free energy which is this
weird kind of enjoyment um without the
more as as as we typically think about
in terms of adaptive uh learning um by
evaluating potential costs uh uh for uh
different policies and things
um and I think that that would be
potentially um one one way of of
bringing those together and it's it's uh
uh the homeo reesus idea is is very uh
interesting where there's this I I can
find it somewhere but there's this
diagram Lan has for the drive um and
it's he draws it as um as as a loop as
an arrow Loop encircling um uh
negativity encircling something that you
never quite hit um and and that's why
the drive has this repetitive logic and
it repeats uh en circles something that
it is aiming at but never quite lands on
in part because uh it has a purely uh
fantasmatic status that there isn't
something that um could finally be hit
um and hence and hence the repetition
continues um so perhaps that that would
be I think um I I think one way
to link the uh to link seeking and EXP
free energy um
through expected free energy for future
that doesn't exist uh nevertheless
exists in the in the unconscious for the
subject
[Music]
um I'll read a question or two from the
live chat okay Andrew writes where do
you place the reality principle in your
mapping in seminar 7 Leon seems to view
it as being in service of the Pleasure
Principle so is it a lesser priority
concept to incorporate
here yeah that that's really great and I
think um I I don't make a huge
distinction because of that that it's
still ultimately in the service of the
Pleasure Principle but um one of the
points that is also made is that the
reality principle not only as a sort of
self-correcting uh mechanism in the
sense of uh learning and updating uh
prior predictions based on uh uh new
experiences in that sense but also Lan
talks about reality principle as um the
index to the the the the maintenance of
a minimal level of tension in the psyche
uh uh the maintenance of um uh from the
the the uh the exigencies of Life uh
that uh cause there to be a certain
minimal constant level of tension and
that that um that that maintenance being
linked to what we've been discussing as
this okay what what does one then do
with this uh uh sort of necessity of
repeating uh uncertainty that has this
uh at least subjectively or or
phenomenologically this paradoxical uh
component to it awesome another question
from the chat for you John or anyone
Kendra wrote does affect Consciousness
itself emerge as a mistake from the
complexity of self-organizing system
if I can speak metaphorically yes as a
mistake but but it's a good mistake and
and it's in the sense of um the um slav
has this uh thing of you know it's
something that happens by accident but
then it was something that turned out to
be to be good you know you trying to
you're you're trying to do something
something goes wrong then oh wow but
this is new and unexpected but it it but
it still works in its own way um like
the making of um games uh novel
invention or making of uh in history you
know different Cuisines or different
foods or cheeses or wines that emerge
because something wrong a mistake
happened in the fermentation process but
oh look now we have this and and now now
this is something that's all wonderful
uh and I I I I think that um that's one
nice way to think about clinical work of
uh and from from a lanan perspective
it's that okay can can something
differently be done or can something new
come from uh this this mistake uh quote
unquote mistake of uh uh how one is uh
maintaining a drive circuit or
maintaining a certain uh repetition of
of uncertainty uh that still sustains it
but in a different
way awesome Bucky Fuller talked about
mistake
mystique and it's sort of a living
systems perspective with the error first
ontology and the vivifying perspective
on the differential rather than like
dust in a motor which will just
inevitably make it more and more off
kilter how are you going to continue
with the work or where is the book and
everything
at uh well the the book is published
very um uh thankfully and um I I I I
can't say exactly where where the next
step is but I'm uh uh going trying to
apply this a little more empirically
uh is is is my my personal hope um Mark
I wanted to invite you you said that you
had a potential point of disagreement
and uh uh I just wanted to make sure you
you could you could air
that um I think that given the time
constraints I won't go down that
particular path um but I I'll rather
pick up on I'm also aware that we must
leave time for Carl to share his screen
because I too would love to see those
references that he has in mind
but um so so I'll just make one final
remark which has to do with the the main
thread of disagreement that I'm pleased
to see we did manage to find uh about um
uh the the equating of Jance with uh
with seeking um and you said uh almost
uh in passing uh and I think almost
embarrassedly you said well leanians
don't like uh to uh to to explain
in this sort of way because it sounds
too adaptive um so I I want to comment
on that and I saw a little frown on
Carl's face when you said that and I
shared the frown without expressing it
so this this is what what I think we we
have to take seriously uh feelings um
you know once they evolved uh they
become part of Nature and they do
something they actually have causal
powers and I think that you know that we
all too easily forget that um now uh the
the feeling of
lust clearly uh the Adaptive uh in other
words why it was selected in why why why
it's such a feeling evolved is because
it encourages us to perform sexual acts
uh which ultimately result in the uh in
reproduction and therefore in the
survival of our species uh but that's
not what motivates each sentient subject
uh to to um to have sex uh what
motivates us is the
feeling and uh the the feeling um very
frequently we want the pleasure without
reproducing we we're hoping not to
reproduce so the the feeling has
motivational power has causal power all
of its own quite independently of the uh
of the
adaptive mechanisms whereby it evolved
now all I wanted to say is the same
applies to seeking uh seeking evolved uh
for the very good reasons that we've
been discussing uh that it is positively
a good thing uh in terms of U long-term
free energy minimization uh to to
positively engage with uncertainty and
to increase your your your your free
energy in the process but the feeling uh
is
has the same relationship uh to that the
feeling in other words the the the in my
view the the the feeling that lon's
talking about the the enjoyment of the
increased um
attention uh the the feeling exists in
its own right and and has its own status
and so you don't know I am engaging with
uncertainty now because in the long run
this is going to reduce my free energy
not at all you're just engaging with
uncertainty because it's
nice and so it feels good uh you know
not why uh and and and I I I still find
that the most satisfactory explanation
for the phenomenon that laon is is is uh
trying to explain there
thanks I've enjoyed this conversation
very much thank you thank you Mark ever
any last words and then Carl you can
share your
screen um yes thank you I also I thought
this discussion was great um yeah I'm
also really interested in um this point
of how expected free energy May
accommodate the phenomena that you
describe in leanian terms especially
maybe when we're dealing with expected
free energy not just in the sense of
what will happen based on my current
beliefs but maybe especially once you
get to the more complicated schemes for
example in the case of Professor
friston's sophisticated inference where
it's not just a matter of what will
happen based on what I believe but also
what will I believe based on what
happens please correct me if I if I I
hope I don't butcher it now but like
where the where the whole the whole
Cascade gets gets um more and more
complicated I kind of disconnected from
the present as it as it proceeds um yeah
yeah that's that that's what I want to
add no you didn't but butcher it at
all it's very sophisticated to mention
sophisticated
inference in um I I'm wondering with the
point that um Mark was alluding to there
is that all the ingredients that go into
the computation of an expected free
energy um and it's just interesting to
know that this some of these ingredients
uh emerge as things called intrinsic
motivation in neur robotics so when
you're actually um if if you're looking
for attachment Theory with robots there
are people who do this a lot um and they
understand that expected the seeking
part of a certain kind very Elemental
kind in terms of intrinsic motivation
which I Al find qu quite quite nice um
sorry but what I was going to say was um
the the the evaluation of all of these
moving parts that contribute to the the
different and potentially conflicting
aspects of the composition of the
expected energy rest upon the
Precision which brings us back to the
Precision now that doesn't come from
Magic it has to come from your
generative model so there has to be a
state of mind that can prescribe and
Implement and switch on the right
precisions in this context and exactly
the way I think both John and Mark were
talking about and I think it's at that
level or possibly even a meta level
above that the the feeling gets into the
game um so it's not the is not the
intrinsic motivation in and of itself
that is felt it is all the enabling of
the prioritization via the precisions
that will Nuance what is intrinsically
motivating what you know what um um you
know what compels me to seek what
compels me to you know and so so forth
and I recognize that this particular
profile of precision is mine and and it
is um associated with this deployment of
the Precision and the activation of the
mechanisms that would be required to to
modulate that so I think the feeling um
could be completely divorced from the
actual um uh expected free energy in the
sense that you know um even if my
expected free energy was was um
non-adaptive in the sense I have
absolutely no idea what to do next I'm
bored there's no more epistemic value in
this environment I have no preferences
um you know I just don't know what's
going you know what what to do what to
do next I may actually see that as a
displeasure thing or a pleasurable thing
um simply because in order to set that
um set that profile I've had to induce a
particular Precision which is apt for
this for this particular particular
context so I think that you know that
metacognitive or deep aspect where um
you need to have that particular depth
to your to your self morals in order to
specify what Precision is up for this
moment may be something that that is you
know allows you a little bit of latitude
in terms of feeling good about what is
completely maladaptive and vice versa um
I don't know I suspect that's that in
part was was a point that uh that that
Mark Mark was making
do you want to share your slides or
papers Carl and then that will be I do
but I I I I I can say it's three minutes
P um we I could just do this for for for
JN and Mark um if um if we're we're
we're over
time
do just do it all right let's just go
and uh um yeah I should apologize feel a
bit naive now I clearly did not
understand the repetition compulsion
and I have to think more about that so
yeah share screen it's going to share
screen in the live chat Carl we're
trying to understand whether reading
your papers is it only about the value
of the
information and and the and the uh the
expected cost of course um I in fact yes
so here we were so this is documentary
proof that I have now taken to referring
to Prior preferences as expected cost so
that you can use this phrase multiple
constraint satisfaction where the cost
um um if like scores the constraints and
just to reemphasize it's a
multi-dimensional has many dimensions as
there are outcomes that one could
possibly sense measure infer or or
observe um so this is from a re the most
recent description of the expected free
energy um um in biological psychology
from the supervised structure learning
but that's uh yeah where there we
are what I thought was um just coming
back to this the the original joke
um um about um the cannibal um the
cannibal eat um um having eaten the last
cannibal on um on the island I um I I
thought that the story was going to be
unpacked in terms of the um the
inability of ourselves to represent
ourselves um and um I'm just compelled
by Chris Field's work in this space
where he stays close to the physics in
his own words to to to demonstrate that
um
self-representation at some level of
recursion and some level of depth is a
mathematical impossibility so I just
wondered whether whether that was um um
what was being intimated uh you know by
that joke it it transpired that it
probably wasn't so important in the
central argument but um I just put this
um paper up um by Chris Fields um and
Mike Levin uh just as a recent treatment
of this from the point of view of the
physics um there is also a treatment of
this from the point of view of
Consciousness um um where in a slightly
more narrative form this you know this
impossibility of seeing oneself or
representing oneself uh at a certain
depth or recursion or sophistication in
an economic sense um inherits from the
notion of an irreducible markof blanket
that can't be um subdivided on the
inside so the only way that this
particular irreducible Markoff blanket
or system in the brain which could be uh
distributed and would certainly include
um the um the sources of neuromodulation
in the spirit of uh Mark's thesis which
is explicitly mentioned in this paper um
the only way that it can see itself is
by acting upon the rest of the brain for
example and that action can only be
through deploying Precision um so I
thought there was a nice point of
contact between the purely mathematical
treatment of self-representation and how
it might be unpacked this is a paper
which is um gone through many many
versions but um um uh talks about the
inner screen model of Consciousness
which is on archives first Au author
ramstead um but Chris was a key uh key
um author of um on that um the um now
that was just reiterating oh yes um I
talking about sort of um we claws
um um could be read in many different
ways um and um you know what one aspect
of this um could be that we're not
talking about deterministic systems
we're talking about stochastic systems
that can only be described
probabilistically another aspect of this
is um the departure from deterministic
systems as we move into real um or um
certainly from the physics protected
biotic systems that have um a a a
chaotic aspect that is often called
or um uh has a mathematical
characteristic of strangeness which is
um um exploited in this treatment of
strange particles um with a sort of
rather uh with poetic license also a
reference to um the strange Loop of
hofstader um but in this instance
speaking exactly to this recurrence so I
now appreciate this is not quite the
repetition compulsion it's more
fundamental but the recurrence that we
were talking about before in terms of
revisiting states that one uh once was
in um but also it's unpacked in a
particular way in terms of what the
physics brings to the table in in terms
of different kinds of things um um and
noticing that um it is certainly
possible to represent your infer your
own actions and that may be the first
step towards a very deep model towards
this irreducible um Markoff blanket uh
where we can no longer represent
ourselves certainly can um at subsequent
or lower levels have a mechanism for
understanding the feelings read as
mental actions on the um the remainder
um so this is a paper by me um with
strange things in the title um this the
S yeah um this one was interesting um
I'd read this with care but it it does
um provide you an entree into um to into
a literature um which actually in this
instance comes from fintech or financial
from
um formal theories in um in finance and
and the like um but it has two aspects
which I thought were were interesting
first of all um it it sort of reiterates
the the focus that at the end of the day
we are quantum um or we can be read as
Quantum systems so that things have a
language like property in the in the in
the sense that they have a certain
discreetness um and secondly the
implications for that um taking a
slightly different view from Chris
Fields when it comes to representing
self and important aspects of
representing self and not just in terms
of self- modeling and the um the ensuing
mechanisms for feelings but in the
immune system it being able to recognize
that this cell this kind of this antigen
um belongs to me or belongs to a virus
is a really important um um aspect of
self representation self-recognition so
I just put this paper up by Sher Marcos
who is um um a fascinating writer but I
repeat it this is difficult stuff but
it's it does highlight biotic elements
have unique digital identifiers with
Geno's executing 3D self assembly for
morphology and so on um and her argument
uses recursive operation of self-
reference
um by appeal to um
um godell or um you can read that
godel's formulation of U of sentences uh
and the implications to
self-replication representation the
interesting thing is she takes the
argument um from math supplies them to
the thy itself in the spirit of
Immunology but then takes it into the
realm of mirror neurons which is getting
slightly closer to uh
um oh leave that one yeah um just a
couple of notes just to say that um you
know the early work um speaking to the
importance of neurom modulation and
precision has a lot of empirical uh
backing in terms of certainly dopamine
encoding the Precision of beliefs about
what I'm going to do next that have this
categorical aspect so there's a lot of
work um suggesting that you know things
certainly things like dopamine have a
profound role um in the feelings
associated with things like seeking this
is the work of um a group of people who
are committed to understanding
phenomenology in a sort of philosophical
sense that highlights and I'm sure you
know about this but really does
highlight um the importance of precision
and specifically conditioning Precision
on higher level representations of self
here referenced in terms of hdden mental
states that themselves are um updated in
accord with fairly more or less precise
beliefs whose Precision themselves are
um encoded by a high level so this is
one example of this
contextualizing um by being able to
recognize yourself in certain states of
mind um either subp personally or not uh
that enable there are associated with
the deployment of precision at lower
levels and so on all the way up until
you reach the this irreducible Markoff
blanket so this is work high level
States condition the likelihood mapping
Precision at the level below so I
thought this was a if you did want to
sort of formalize this and start to
simulate these things this is the kind
of model I think you'd refer to and uh
lar sfed Smith is a sort of one of the
key authors in in the in that space so
towards a computational phology and
mental action
um that right and then finally oh yeah
we don't need to worry that but I I I
just put that up to remind myself um
that more recent leveraging of these
discret State space models um now can be
read purely in terms of you know
inductive inference of a logical
symbolic sort um which if if you like is
another way of um motivating the
importance of this language like way in
which we um build beliefs about what we
are going to do can be read uh at one
level when they're very precise as
intentional Behavior so I thought that
might be um an interesting endorsement
of the
um um some of the points that were being
made earlier on and would stopped my
sharing that was
it thank you all wonderful thank you so
much so much thank you all right good
luck with everything John thank you all
for
joining byebye
yeah I understand um folks have to go
can I just at least for recording sake
um if folks have to go that's fine just
so I can say and this so hope me remind
myself what I'm saying yeah um people
can depart yeah people can depart the
live stream continues and then John if
you want to add any closing notes yeah
just so on the Adaptive Point um uh and
I I I think that a lot of the resistance
is just resistance uh even clinically
speaking um uh but um I I think um the
the the the trick and the challenge and
I I I think the uh the the papers you
referenced um uh and shared I I I
haven't read them but um I I from how
you described them I think that they uh
would be approaching similar uh ideas um
but the the difficulty of uh again
addressing this point that sort of
resists full sort of capture resists
full sort of uh
resolution or explanation and and how
exactly to think about that especially
when uh as as I said one will kind of
repeat something in and it doesn't lead
to uh an Adaptive outcome and yet this
continues to repeat but then what to do
with it in a way that allows uh someone
to kind of uh enjoy a bit a bit
differently or or in another way um that
I think would be fine to be called um
adaptive but again uh uh adaptive maybe
in in in in this sense of uh maintaining
these sort of different Paths of um
again error uh again uh Paths of uh
expected free energy that uh continue to
sort of persist um uh yeah so just to
kind of tie that together I I think that
that's um uh the the the cannibal who
makes the mistake of eating the last
Cannibal and then okay what what is he
to do now um with with with his oral
Drive um so I'll I'll I'll stop with
that but thank you again so much um this
was really a a wonderful
treat thank you thank you thank you you
everyone bye bye thank
you e